Association for Women in Mathematics records SSC.MS.00796
Sophia Smith Collection
Association for Women in Mathematics records
1970-2018
Sophia Smith Collection
Association for Women in Mathematics (U.S.)
SSC.MS.00796
33.5 linear feet (26 record cartons, 1 flat box, 1 medium card file)
11 items (6 floppy disks and 5 compact discs)
3 Gigabytes (332 files)
The Association for Women in Mathematics (AWM) is a professional society whose mission is to encourage women and girls to study and to have active careers in the mathematical sciences, and to promote equal opportunity for and the equal treatment of women and girls in the mathematical sciences. This collection includes materials relating to the Association's founding and management, as well as newsletters, grant and travel grant records, publications, and information on prizes, contests, workshops, and conferences held by the Association for Women in Mathematics.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sent to Special Collections via Karoline Pershell. Materials were in storage in Pershell's father-in-law's law office.
Biographical / Historical
The Association for Women in Mathematics (AWM) is a professional society whose mission is to encourage women and girls to study and to have active careers in the mathematical sciences, and to promote equal opportunity for and the equal treatment of women and girls in the mathematical sciences. The AWM was founded in 1971, and since has grown to approximately 5200 members, including over 250 institutional members, including colleges, universities, institutes, and mathematical societies. Supported primarily through federal grants, AWM offers numerous programs and workshops to mentor women and girls in the mathematical sciences, as well as prizes and contests to motivate girls to learn more about women mathematicians and inspire them to pursue mathematics. For more information, see their Web site: https://sites.google.com/site/awmmath/home
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Content Description
This collection includes materials relating to the Association's founding and management, including membership and information on organizational partners. Also included are newsletters (hard and digital copies), grant and travel grant records, publications (such as event brochures, books, and informational pamphlets), and information on prizes, contests, lecture series, workshops, and conferences held by the Association for Women in Mathematics. Digital files include documents, images, and audio recordings related to Sonia Kovalesky "Math for Girls" Day events, 2000-2011
Mathematicians; Women mathematicians--History; Women in higher education.; Electronic records; Association for Women in Mathematics (U.S.); Association for Women in Mathematics (U.S.)
- I. Administration, 1; 7.5 linear feet (5 record cartons)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes founding records, employee records and membership lists, correspondence, promotional materials, and information about committees overseeing various projects within the Association.
  - Incorporation papers and organization bylaws, 1973-2005; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 1, Box 4)
    - By-laws, 1991 December; 1 items (1 floppy disk); 0.000081 Gigabytes (1 MS Word document) (Box 1)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access.
  - Financial information, 1997-2005; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Executive committee meetings notes and reports, 1973-2008; 17 folders (17 folders) (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Executive committee handbooks, 2009-2012; 4 items (4 books) (Box 1)
  - Local meeting reports and notes, 1980-1984; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Speakers' Bureau information, funding requests, and reports, 1979-1985; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Directory of members, staff, and local coordinators, 1975-1988; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Careers correspondence and information on related organizations, 1979-1987; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Meetings on lectures, prize committees, and poster projects, 2005-2008; 70 folders (70 folders) (Box 2)
  - AWM Newsletters, 1971-2010; 2 items (compact discs); 3 Gigabytes (257 PDF files) (Box 2)
    Other Finding Aids
    See the attached log file for a list of media that was copied. More detailed digital file lists are available upon request.
  - Combined membership list and membership database information, 2006; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Administrative membership information on dues, renewal, gift memberships, and services, 2005-2008; 14 folders (14 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Promotional materials, including flyers, pamphlets, banners, advertisements, and website and listserv information, 2005-2008; 16 folders (16 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Administrative correspondence, 1972-1997; 43 folders (43 folders) (Box 4, Box 5)
  - Address cards (individuals and organizations), 1971-1988; .5 linear feet (1 medium card file box) (Box 27)
- II. Research and travel grants, 2; 5 linear feet (3.5 record cartons)
  - Grants received list, 1973-1986 (Box 6)
  - Proposal to the Rockefeller Family Fund, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Final grant reports, various organizations and events, 1997-2004; 11 folders (11 folders) (Box 6)
  - AWM 40th Anniversary funding grants, 2011-2012; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Department of Energy (DOE) funding and final report, 2007-2015; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Office of Naval Research (ONR) grants, 1991-2015; 12 folders (12 folders) (Box 6)
  - "Indirect Cost Rate" of digital file, 2006 August 14; 1 items (1 compact disc); 0.0003 Gigabytes (2 digital files) (Box 6)
    "AMW Office of Naval Research Audit, Original proposal, FY 04-05" (2 PDF files)
  - Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR) grants, 2000-2005; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Air Force Office of Scientific Research digital files, approximately 2000; 1 items (1 floppy disk); 0.0003 Gigabytes 8 files (MS Word docs and pdfs) (Box 7)
    See attached digital file list for more information
  - National Security Agency (NSA) grants, 1995-2011; 14 folders (14 folders) (Box 7)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) proposals and travel grants, 1990-2012; 20 folders (20 folders) (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Exxon grants, 1994-2006; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Hewlett Packard grants, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 8)
  - Mathematical Science Research Institute (MSRI) grants, 1996; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Microsoft grants, 1999; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 8)
  - Sloan Foundation grants, 1993-1995; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 8)
  - Toyota grants, 2000-2001; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Specific project grants, 2002-2004; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Travel grants, 1988-2006; 12 folders (12 folders) (Box 8, Box 9)
- III. Programming, 3; 1.5 linear feet (1 record carton)
  - Sonia Kovalevsky Math for Girls Day
    - SK Days (various high schools and universities), 1985-2013; 5 linear feet (3.5 record cartons) (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
    - SK packet edits, 1993-1997; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - Sonya Kovalesky Math for Girls Day: digital files, 2000-2011; .13 Gigabytes (66 digital files); 6 items (4 floppy disks, 2 compact discs) (Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
      Applications, images, and audio recordings related to Sonia Kovalesky "Math for Girls" Day events, 2000-2011. For more information see attached log file
      See the attached log file for a list of media copied. More detailed digital file lists are available upon request.
  - Workshops, Conferences, and Lecture Series
    - Julia Robinson Celebration of Women in Mathematics applications, info packets, speakers, 1996; 11 folders (11 folders) (Box 13)
    - Olga Taussky Todd (OTT) conference information packets, speaker selection, evaluation forms, 1999; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 13)
    - Mathfest correspondence and information, 2005-2007; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - AWM at Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) conferences, 1991-2010; 6.75 linear feet (4.5 record cartons) (Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18)
      - "Past Funded AWM Workshop Participants", 1991-2000; 1 items (1 floppy disk) (Box 17)
    - AWM at Joint Mathematics Meetings (JMM), 2005-2008; 2 linear feet (1.5 record cartons) (Box 18, Box 19)
    - Emmy Noether Lecture bio material, speaker selection, correspondence, preparation and funding, and booklets, 1982-2009; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 23)
  - Prizes and Essay Contests
    - Association for Women in Mathematics essay contest (middle, high, university, and graduate school), 2001-2004; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Ruth I. Michler Memorial Prize committee agreements, correspondence, applicants, 2006-2007; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Louise Hay Award information, nominations, applications, and brochures, 1991-2009; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 3, Box 22)
      - Digital files, "98 Hay: 9th Annual to be presented 1/99 in San Antonio", 1998; 1 items (1 floppy disk) (Box 22)
    - Alice T. Schafer prize applications, notification letters, and news bulletins, 1990-2010; 3 linear feet (2 record cartons) (Box 20, Box 21)
- IV. Publications, 4
  - Newsletters
    - President's Reports, 1971-1992; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Newsletters, 1971-2017; 3 linear feet (2 record cartons) (Box 24, Box 25)
  - Other
    - Pamphlets, 2000-2015; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Membership directories, 1994-1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Careers in Math, 1976, 1980s, 1994, 1996; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Speakers' Bureau booklets, 1978-1987; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Flyers and pamphlets for symposiums, conferences, 1976-1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Newsletters from related organizations, 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 5)
    - Joint Mathematics meetings, Prizes and Awards, 2004-2016 (Box 28)
    - Joint Mathematics meetings, Program, 2006-2015 (Box 28)
    - American Mathematical Society, Semi-centennial and Centennial pamphlets, 1938-1988 (Box 28)
    - Mathematical Association of America conference program, 2015 (Box 28)
    - Notices of the American Mathematical Society, Vol. 63, no. 1, 2016 (Box 28)
  - Books
    - Bhama Srinivasan and Judith Sally, eds., Emmy Noether in Bryn Mawr (2 copies), 1983 (Box 28)
    - Bettye Anne Case and Anne M. Leggett, eds., Complexities: Women in Mathematics, 2005 (Box 28)
    - Linda Keen, ed., "The Legacy of Sonya Kovalevskaya," in Contemporary Mathematics, Vol. 64, 1987 (Box 28)
    - Sandra Z. and Philip Keith, eds., Proceedings of the National Conference on Women in Math and the Sciences, 1990 (Box 28)
- V. Memorabilia, 5; .5 linear feet (1 flat box)
  - SK Days memorabilia (packet, ruler, pins, drawstring bag), 2005; 4 items (drawstring tote, two pins, information packet for Southern Louisiana University's SK Days event) (Box 26)
  - AWM corporation founding charter (Massachusetts), 1973 September 11; 1 items (1 item) (Box 26)